<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0"
  xml:id="Herzman-FourRomances-Export-12-Athelston-Intro-tei">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Introduction to Athelston</title>
        <author>Herzman, Ronald B.</author>
        <author>Drake, Graham</author>
        <author>Salisbury, Eve</author>
        <sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
        <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
        <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Amster, Mara I.</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Church, Jennifer</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Conrath, Ryan</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-09">Collected metadata</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-04">Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Encoded TEI</resp>
          <resp from="2025-08" to="2025-09">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-09">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-09">Formatted for XML export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Johnson-Olin, Martha M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName>
          <resp from="2023-12" to="2023-12">Collected metadata</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lupack, Alan</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>McShane, Kara L.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Roth, Aaron</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Saupe, Karen</persName>
          <resp>Collated and entered corrections</resp>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Encoded in TEI in 2025.</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
        </availability>
        <date/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Mara I. Amster</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Melissa Bernstein</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Jennifer Church</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rita Copeland</persName>
          <orgName>University of Minnesota</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Angela Gibson</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lisa J. Kiser</persName>
          <orgName>Ohio State University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Alan Lupack</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Russell A. Peck</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Ian Peddie</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Ann Robinson</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas H. Seiler</persName>
          <orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName>
          <orgName>University of Florida</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>John William Sutton</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Dana M. Symons</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName>
          <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <editor>Herzman, Ronald B.</editor>
            <editor>Drake, Graham</editor>
            <editor>Salisbury, Eve</editor>
            <title>Four Romances of England: King Horn, Havelok the Dane, Bevis of Hampton,
              Athelston</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
              <date>1999</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary
          texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered
          between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both
          affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the
          Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly
          interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and
          filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny
          from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to
          someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS
          publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and
          certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and
          apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other
          manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to
          ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original
          language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers
          expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s),
          textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and
          thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that
          set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor,
          congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current
          bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi
            rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
        <correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in
            order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and
            typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on
            Github:
            https://github.com/mets-editions/herzman-fourromances/blob/main/herzman-fourromances-export-corrections-log.xlsx</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>First edition published in 1999</change>
      <change>Encoded in HTML</change>
      <change>Entered editorial corrections in 2025</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <anchor xml:id="Herzman-FourRomances-Export-12-Athelston-Intro"/>
      <div type="text">
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">It would seem that <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>, a relatively
          brief romance of 812 lines dating from the late fourteenth century, should pose few
          problems for the modern editor, existing as it does without any known direct source and
          surviving in only one manuscript. But that is not the case. Rather, this short romance
          perhaps even more than the longer romances presented in this volume raises a number of
          questions about historical backgrounds, sources and analogues, the poet’s agenda, as well
          as textual and aesthetic matters. Early scholars, for instance, have seen in it references
          to events ranging in date from the tenth to the late fourteenth centuries, including the
          struggle between Henry II and Thomas Becket and the challenge of the barons to Richard
            II.<note target="#1" type="footnotelink">1</note> Still others point to a historical
          Wymound, found guilty of simony in 1102, or to the events taking place during the reign of
          King John. The poem’s source is also contested. A. M. Trounce claims repeatedly that there
          is a French original lurking in the archival shadows, despite the obvious local colors,
          place names, and details of English custom and law.<note target="#2" type="footnotelink"
            >2</note> Laura Hibbard Loomis argues that the poem’s origin resides in the legend of
          Queen Emma and the Ploughshares, a story of the mother of Edward the Confessor.<note
            target="#3" type="footnotelink">3</note> A frequently mentioned literary analogue is the
          Middle English <hi rend="italic">Amis and Amiloun</hi>, but several of the poem’s motifs
          are common to other works. The diversity of scholarly views on these matters suggests the
          presence of an amazingly complex intertextuality and interpretive potential for this
          seemingly simple romance.</p>
        <p style="body" n="1">Neither is the plot as straightforward as it appears to be at first.
          Rather, the poem’s unfolding of betrayal and treachery is brought to a happy resolution
          only after a series of deferrals and unveilings, made more suspenseful by the intensified
          action and heightened psychological intrigue, an effect the poet gains by mirroring
          characters’ identities and constructing vivid and dramatic narrative events. The poem
          begins simply enough: four men, described as messengers, swear an oath of brotherhood and
          truth to each other. One of them, Athelston, becomes king when the king his cousin dies.
          Athelston then makes two of his sworn brothers earls and the third Archbishop of
          Canterbury. Here is where the intrigue begins with something akin to sibling rivalry. One
          of these earls, the Earl of Stone, remains true to him; the other, however, the Earl of
          Dover, is false, betraying his brother by accusing him of treachery to the king. The king
          believes the Earl of Dover, and resolves to kill the alleged traitor and his family, but
          before he does the queen sends a messenger to the Archbishop who comes to London to plead
          for the life of his friend. The king first refuses to listen, and there follows a fierce
          struggle between the king and the archbishop. It seems as though the king is going to win,
          but he relents when the archbishop gains support from the people. An ordeal by fire
          establishes the innocence of the Earl of Stone and the guilt of the traitor; the romance
          ends with the spectacle of the traitor’s death.</p>
        <p style="body" n="2">In his introduction to his edition Donald Sands implies that <hi
            rend="italic">Athelston</hi> has an overly high reputation. He suggests that the poem is
          indeed very impressive on first reading but that the closer one looks, the less one
            sees.<note target="#4" type="footnotelink">4</note> As an introduction to the poem, this
          is not a bad characterization, suggesting as it does that the poem depends on a kind of
          surface attraction, which is surely there. But it is probably not an altogether just
          estimation. Sands is no doubt correct when he states that one will not find overly subtle
          character portraits in the work, though the credulity of the king, the resoluteness of the
          archbishop, and the villainy of the traitor all show touches which go beyond simple fairy
          tale opposition between good and evil. Dieter Mehl is not wrong when he says that the
          characters are both memorable and individualized.<note target="#5" type="footnotelink"
            >5</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="3">Not only are the four main characters — Athelston the King, the Earls
          of Dover and Stone, and the Archbishop — memorable for their powerful positions,
          personalities, and confrontations with one another, but the supporting characters are also
          unforgettably drawn. The messenger, who is employed by the king, the queen, and several
          earls, is described early in the poem as a “foundling” but later, as a “noble man,” stands
          in stark contrast, even acts as an alter-ego, to the king whose name he bears.<note
            target="#6" type="footnotelink">6</note> His stalwart endurance and professional
          integrity in delivering messages to the right people at the right time despite the
          grueling distances between stops exposes the lack of steadfastness in the king. The
          messenger does not waiver in his moral obligations — the king does. The very office of
          messenger resonates with the four main characters; described as messengers from “dyvers
          cuntré” they come into England to fulfill the obligations of their profession — one of
          which is the necessity for conveying the truth, the very oath they swear to seal their
          bond of brotherhood. A subsequent elevation in status — a result of Athelston’s fortuitous
          rise to kingship — confers political power on those who otherwise would not have it and
          prepares the way for testing the integrity of their oath to one another. The inevitable
          corruptive forces accompanying such a quick rise in prestige follow, as Wymound soon falls
          prey to envy; true nobility is not associated with rank and social status, but rather with
          moral character.</p>
        <p style="body" n="4">The typical tail-rhyme stanza in <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>
          consists of four rhymed couplets, each of which is followed by a tail rhyme which remains
          constant throughout the stanza, so that the rhyme scheme of the twelve-line stanza in the
          poem is <hi rend="italic">aab</hi><hi rend="italic"> ccb ddb eeb</hi>. Perhaps taking his
          cue from Chaucer’s parody of romance in The Tale of Sir Thopas, Sands is also critical of
          the rhyme scheme of the work, objecting both to what he sees as the monotony of tail rhyme
          and also to the apparent inconsistency of several irregular stanzas. Here too his judgment
          is probably overly harsh. Kevin Kiernan contends that this stanzaic structure helps
          account for the integrated character of the work and that variations in the poem are
          purposeful. He stretches his point, perhaps, when he says that the poem is more closely
          knit than <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>, but he nonetheless makes
          a convincing case for the artistry of the work.<note target="#7" type="footnotelink"
            >7</note> A. M. Trounce sees tail rhyme as an opportunity to exercise the imagination;
          poetic diction often generates a number of interpretative possibilities. The tail-rhyme
          poets also have a flare for the dramatic — the scene of cruelty to the queen, the unrobing
          and extended trial by ordeal, including the testing of the earl’s two sons and pregnant
          wife, the birth of St. Edmund immediately following the ordeal, the spectacular execution
          of Wymound, a traitor every bit as treacherous as Ganelon or Judas. His body, singed by
          fire, hanged, and left dangling by decree, marks the point at which the poet makes his
          conventional exit.</p>
        <p style="body" n="5">Like the noble messenger, the female characters are models of
          integrity and perseverance. Dame Edyff, awaiting the impending birth of a third child when
          Wymound’s false message arrives, refuses to stay at home where safe delivery would be more
          certain. Rather, she decides to accompany her husband and sons to London in order to
          witness what she expects to be a great honor. Instead, the entire family is taken into
          custody at the order of a king whose good judgment, by this time, has been transformed by
          Wymound’s treachery. Despite the hardship of captivity, however, Dame Edyff not only
          manages to survive but shortly thereafter endures the onset of labor in the midst of the
          ordeal by fire. It is only after she has successfully walked over the burning ploughshares
          that she gives birth to another son, the child-saint Edmund. Just as the deeds of the
          noble messenger reveal the lack of integrity in Wymound, the birth of Edmund recalls the
          cruelty of the king to his pregnant wife and her subsequent miscarriage of the rightful
          heir to the throne. Like Edyff, the queen endures great suffering. Unlike Edyff, however,
          her purpose in the narrative is to dramatize the extent to which the king has fallen from
          rational judgment. As Elizabeth Ashman Rowe argues, the queen’s miscarriage signifies
          beyond the tragedy of the event itself; it points directly to the king’s miscarriage of
            justice.<note target="#8" type="footnotelink">8</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="6">In the struggle between the king and the archbishop, an English
          audience would no doubt be reminded of the encounter between Henry II and Thomas Becket,
          the famous conflict which ended with the murder of Becket in 1170. Other probable
          historical analogues in the poem would include the name Athelston itself (hero of the
          battle of Brunanburh), and the reference to the birth of St. Edmund (of East Anglia) at
          the end of the poem. Rowe locates the poem in a specific fourteenth-century context. For
          Athelston the King we may substitute the tyrannical Richard II, who dispensed with due
          process for his rivals, whom he then unlawfully imprisoned, exiled, or executed.<note
            target="#9" type="footnotelink">9</note> The specificity of these historical allusions
          should not allow us to overlook the larger issues which the poem embodies. Indeed, one of
          the signal strengths of the poem is that the legendary material out of which it is
          constructed has become the vehicle for embodying some of the large concerns of the Middle
          Ages. Clearly the most central of these is the relationship between the secular and the
          ecclesiastical spheres. This struggle provides the central dramatic conflict in the poem
          in its vivid and energetic presentation of threat and counter threat by king and bishop.
          Its implications are far wider than the probable specific allusion to the Becket
          controversy, however much it may follow the contours of that controversy in insisting on
          distinct limits to royal power and in seeing ecclesiastical privilege as a check on royal
          tyranny. As W. R. J. Barron has pointed out, the defiance of tyranny in the name of
          brotherhood and the importance of the rule of law emerge as key themes in the work.<note
            target="#10" type="footnotelink">10</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="7">Another of the larger issues is contained in the way the poem handles
          the question of good and evil. The poem provides a clear statement of the cause of the
          betrayal of King Athelston and the Earl of Stone. The Earl of Dover committed his sin not
          out of greed, but out of envy. As he poignantly tells us immediately before his death
          (speaking of the king’s relationship to the Earl of Stone and to himself): “He lovyd him
          to mekyl and me to lyte; / Therfore envye I hadde” (lines 799–800). At this point, the
          moral implications are more important than the political ones, or perhaps to put it in
          slightly different terms, this ending shows us how, as in most significant medieval
          narratives, the moral and the political cannot be meaningfully separated from each
          other.</p>
        <p style="body" n="8">Sands states that the audience of <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>
          must have been made up of small tradesmen, “very conscious of the history of their
          country, very well aware of its traditions, and very sensitive to the authoritarian habit
          of kings.”<note target="#11" type="footnotelink">11</note> It is not necessary to be quite
          this restrictive in recreating the audience of <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>,
          especially since the poem is one of many poems written in English for an emerging,
          influential middle-class.<note target="#12" type="footnotelink">12</note> There is, in
          fact, some evidence of a middle-class perspective, particularly if we look to the amusing
          presentation of the hard-working messenger. Of all the characters a middle-class audience
          might identify with in the poem, he is the most probable, since the king himself, in his
          rashness, gullibility, and stubbornness, is not especially sympathetic.<note target="#13"
            type="footnotelink">13</note> Whether or not we want to accept this parallel, it should
          at least open us to the possibility of a work which is very carefully structured and whose
          structure, like many medieval romances, is dependent on the careful paralleling of large
          and small units of meaning.</p>

      </div>
      <div type="footnotes">

        <note type="footnote" n="1"><space rend="indent1"/>In <hi rend="italic">Athelston: A Middle
            English Romance</hi>, EETS o.s. 224 (London: Oxford University Press, 1951) A. McI.
          Trounce argues that Alryke resembles Stephen Langton more than Thomas Becket but also sees
          a strong historical resemblance between Alryke and William Bateman of Norwich
          (1344–53).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="2"><space rend="indent1"/>See also Kurt Beug, “Die Sage von König
          Athelstan,” <hi rend="italic">Archiv</hi> 148 (1925), 181–95, for a discussion of the
          relevance of the Queen Emma legend and the existence of a historical Wymound found guilty
          of simony in 1102.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="3"><space rend="indent1"/>See Laura Hibbard Loomis, <hi
            rend="italic">Mediæval Romance in England: </hi><hi rend="italic">A Study of the Sources
            and Analogues of the Non-</hi><hi rend="italic">Cycle Metrical Romances</hi> (New York:
          Burt Franklin, 1960), pp. 143–46.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="4"><space rend="indent1"/>Donald B. Sands, ed., <hi rend="italic"
            >Middle English Verse Romances</hi> (New York: Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, 1966), p.
          130.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="5"><space rend="indent1"/>Dieter Mehl, <hi rend="italic">The Middle
            English Romances of the Thirteenth and Fourteenth </hi><hi rend="italic">Centuries</hi>
          (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1968), p. 148.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="6"><space rend="indent1"/>A. Inskip Dickerson, “The Subplot of the
          Messenger in <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Papers on Language and
            Literature</hi> 12 (1976), 121.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="7"><space rend="indent1"/>Kevin S. Kiernan, “<hi rend="italic"
            >Athelston</hi> and the Rhyme of the English Romances,” <hi rend="italic">Modern
            Language Quarterly</hi> 36 (1975), 340–41.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="8"><space rend="indent1"/>Elizabeth Ashman Rowe, “The Female Body
          Politic and the Miscarriage of Justice in <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>,” <hi
            rend="italic">Studies in the Age of Chaucer</hi> 17 (1995), 79–98.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="9"><space rend="indent1"/>Rowe, p. 88.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="10"><space rend="indent1"/>W. R. J. Barron, <hi rend="italic"
            >English </hi><hi rend="italic">Medieval Romance</hi> (London: Longman, 1987), p.
          81.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="11"><space rend="indent1"/>Sands, p. 131.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="12"><space rend="indent1"/>See Derek Pearsall, “The Development of
          Middle English Romances,” <hi rend="italic">Medieval Studies</hi> 27 (1965),
          91–116.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="13"><space rend="indent1"/>Dickerson, p. 121.</note>


      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
