<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0"
  xml:id="Herzman-FourRomances-Export-06-Havelok-Intro-tei">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Introduction to Havelok the Dane</title>
        <author>Herzman, Ronald B.</author>
        <author>Drake, Graham</author>
        <author>Salisbury, Eve</author>
        <sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
        <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
        <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Amster, Mara I.</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Church, Jennifer</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Conrath, Ryan</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-09">Collected metadata</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-04">Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Encoded TEI</resp>
          <resp from="2025-08" to="2025-09">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-09">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-09">Formatted for XML export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Johnson-Olin, Martha M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName>
          <resp from="2023-12" to="2023-12">Collected metadata</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lupack, Alan</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>McShane, Kara L.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Roth, Aaron</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Saupe, Karen</persName>
          <resp>Collated and entered corrections</resp>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Encoded in TEI in 2025.</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
        </availability>
        <date/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Mara I. Amster</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Melissa Bernstein</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Jennifer Church</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rita Copeland</persName>
          <orgName>University of Minnesota</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Angela Gibson</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lisa J. Kiser</persName>
          <orgName>Ohio State University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Alan Lupack</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Russell A. Peck</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Ian Peddie</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Ann Robinson</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas H. Seiler</persName>
          <orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName>
          <orgName>University of Florida</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>John William Sutton</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Dana M. Symons</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName>
          <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <editor>Herzman, Ronald B.</editor>
            <editor>Drake, Graham</editor>
            <editor>Salisbury, Eve</editor>
            <title>Four Romances of England: King Horn, Havelok the Dane, Bevis of Hampton,
              Athelston</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
              <date>1999</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary
          texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered
          between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both
          affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the
          Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly
          interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and
          filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny
          from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to
          someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS
          publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and
          certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and
          apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other
          manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to
          ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original
          language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers
          expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s),
          textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and
          thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that
          set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor,
          congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current
          bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi
            rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
        <correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in
            order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and
            typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on
            Github:
            https://github.com/mets-editions/herzman-fourromances/blob/main/herzman-fourromances-export-corrections-log.xlsx</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>First edition published in 1999</change>
      <change>Encoded in HTML</change>
      <change>Entered editorial corrections in 2025</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <anchor xml:id="Herzman-FourRomances-Export-06-Havelok-Intro"/>
      <div type="text">
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">Most scholars place <hi rend="italic">Havelok the Dane</hi> at
          the end of the thirteenth century, between 1280 and 1290, and see it as a reworking of
          Anglo-Norman sources.<note target="#1" type="footnotelink">1</note>
          <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> opens with the unfortunate childhood of the English
          princess Goldeboru, Havelok’s future wife, orphaned when her father, the good King
          Athelwold dies, leaving her inadvertently in the hands of a wicked foster parent and
          protector, Godrich. The scene then shifts to Havelok’s own similar childhood in Denmark.
          When Havelok’s father King Birkabein dies, he and his two sisters are left in the care of
          the treacherous usurper, Godard, who cuts the throats of the two young girls and threatens
          the life of Havelok. The little boy, in a demonstration of courage well beyond his years,
          negotiates a promise of fealty in exchange for his life. But instead of accepting
          Havelok’s fealty, Godard hands the boy over to a fisherman, Grim, with instructions to
          kill him. Bound and gagged, the young prince is then transported to his would-be
          executioner’s hut. Before the deed can be done, however, Grim and his wife see a
          mysterious light coming from the boy’s mouth while he sleeps, and a “kynmerk,” the
          cross-shaped birthmark of a king on his shoulder, which convinces them of Havelok’s
          divinely appointed royal status. Then, in a manner reminiscent of fairy tales, Grim fakes
          the child’s death and then takes his whole family along with the boy to England, where
          Havelok grows into a young man who earns his bread first as a fisherman and then as a
          porter.</p>
        <p style="body" n="1">At this point, Godrich forcibly marries Goldeboru to Havelok, thinking
          he is a commoner, a misidentification with which Goldeboru concurs until, on their wedding
          night, the “kynmerk” and the strange light reveal Havelok’s true identity. Her misgivings
          about Havelok’s nobility thus assuaged, soon thereafter Goldeboru and Havelok make their
          way to Denmark, where Havelok poses as a merchant while staying at the house of Ubbe, a
          Danish earl, only to have his identity as true king affirmed once again by the light and
          the birthmark. Havelok avenges the murder of his sisters and wins back the Danish throne
          from Godard and his forces. Havelok then returns to England with Goldeboru to regain her
          kingdom from Godrich (who is flayed and hanged at a slow, merciless rate); he arranges the
          marriages of Grim’s two daughters to English noblemen (one of whom is newly elevated from
          his position as cook), distributes property to his Danish subalterns, and accepts the
          crown of England which he rules with Goldeboru. To Ubbe, he bequeaths the rulership of
          Denmark. Together Havelok and Goldeboru have fifteen children — queens and kings all — and
          live to a comfortable old age.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="1">The Hero’s Body</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="2">In <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi>, as in <hi rend="italic"
            >Horn</hi> we have another romance hero whose very body is central to the narrative. The
          most obvious recurring devices — the supernatural light shining from the sleeping hero’s
          mouth, and the cross-shaped birthmark on his shoulder — appear three times at crucial
          moments in the story: when Grim is about to kill him as a boy; when he has been forcibly
          married to a very distressed Goldeboru; and when he is staying with Ubbe in Denmark at the
          commencement of his campaign to win back the land of his birth. Not only is Havelok’s body
          marked by divine authority, but he is noticeably taller than the other men around him.
          Like the biblical King Saul, he stands out in a crowd: he has a royal bearing that
          separates him from the ordinary. Havelok also consumes more food than ordinary men, a fact
          that motivates the hero to seek employment and contribute to the support of his foster
          family. But in order to avoid calling attention to himself while working among the English
          locals, he shrouds his body in disguises: at Lincoln he dresses no more remarkably than
          his foster family in Grimsby does in order to apprentice as a cook. His disguise is akin
          to that of Sir Gareth, who serves as a “kitchen knave” in Malory’s <hi rend="italic">Le
            Morte Darthur</hi>.<note target="#2" type="footnotelink">2</note> When Havelok arrives
          in Denmark to visit Ubbe, he presents himself as a merchant; by the end of the poem, he is
          wearing the crown of England. But whether his body is a <hi rend="italic">tabula rasa</hi>
          for a heaven-sent sign, or a frame for clothing from every social stratum, his bodily
          strength is remarked on consistently throughout his story. He gains the respect of Lincoln
          locals by winning popular wrestling and stone-throwing contests. He is formidable in
          battle even when he wields unconventional weapons — from an ax to a club or door bar —
          against opponents more conventionally armed. Just as Horn’s beauty is constantly remarked
          upon and celebrated, so too is Havelok’s extra-ordinary physique and prowess.<note
            target="#3" type="footnotelink">3</note></p>
        <p style="heading" n="2"><hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> and the Body Politic</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="3">If attention to Havelok’s body literally underscores the hero’s
          physical attributes and royal status then so too does it represent the political virtues
          of a potential king. Havelok is a walking metaphor for kingship, literally marked with a
          sign of royalty. Thus it is no coincidence that the poem begins with the death of the
          English king, Athelwold, with a description of his rule, followed shortly thereafter by
          the death of the Danish king, Birkabein, and a similar description. Athelwold, we are
          told, establishes peace and justice in a realm rife with treachery and violence, an
          accomplishment for which he is recognized by his subjects — young and old, from every
          estate — as a wise and effective monarch. Both loved and feared, Athelwold demonstrates
          compassion in his “gode werkes,” while, at the same time, he adjudicates criminal acts to
          the fullest extent of medieval English law. When the scene shifts to Denmark, we discover
          that King Birkabein embodies similar personal and political virtues. He too renders
          equitable justice and secures peace and harmony in the kingdom of Denmark. Each king
          provides a model of rulership that fosters social and political stability in their
          respective realms and functions to assure the continuance of the “office” of monarch when
          the king dies. In this sense, the king has not one body but two: he represents both
          himself as individual, with a natural body subject to disease, decay, and death, while at
          the same time he represents the body politic.<note target="#4" type="footnotelink"
            >4</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="2">Made most famous by John of Salisbury in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Policraticus</hi>, a twelfth-century treatise on political philosophy, the body politic
          is a metaphor for hierarchical corporate entities organized with the “head” (the king or
          prince in this case) at its apex, governing the lower members, construed either as classes
          of society or particular groups. Each member of the corporate body in this system is
          expected to contribute to the welfare of the whole organism in order to enhance the
          quality of communal life. At the center of the body politic, or at its heart, reside the
          dual laws — divine and positive — by which the organism operates. Just as the king’s
          subjects are obligated to submit to his authority, so too is he obligated by divine law to
          govern his subjects ethically. Should he fail to honor the precepts under which he rules,
          the king ceases to function as the site of reason for the corporate body; he ceases to be
          a just king and instead becomes a tyrant. Given the paradigms of kingship established
          early in the poem, Havelok’s ultimate destiny is to rule the corporate body so that all
          its members function in a state of health and well-being. His “kynmerk” represents his
          divinely ordained right to sovereignty.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="3"><hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> and Social Class</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="4">While the expected romance love-interest appears in Havelok’s
          relationship with Goldeboru, their marriage is born as much of necessity as romantic love;
          it creates a social and political alliance that confers legitimacy upon their dual cause
          to reclaim the rightful inheritance of each. In his battle against Godard and Godrich,
          Havelok exhibits courage and a sense of avenging justice. He dispatches Godard without
          second thoughts; Godrich requires another strategy, however, since he is an English
          nobleman given stewardship over Athelwold’s daughter by the king himself. No doubt this
          factors into Havelok’s offer of mercy. But when the unrepentant Godrich rejects the gift,
          he must face the legal consequences of his traitorous acts. Havelok’s actions in this
          regard are not motivated by a romantic code of chivalry, but rather by a desire to protect
          the social order of his adopted land, and to uphold popular values of English society.
          This is one reason that the poem seems to express the desires of what J. Halverson calls
          the upward mobility “of the prosperous, hard-working middle class.”<note target="#5"
            type="footnotelink">5</note> Indeed, the work ethic, demonstrated by Havelok’s desire to
          support not only himself, but also his foster family and, subsequently, the larger
          community, contributes to what Susan Crane describes as “an ideology of cohesion in which
          all people share an understanding of good and right, and each class’ duties contribute to
          the common purpose of achieving and maintaining social order.”<note target="#6"
            type="footnotelink">6</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="3"><hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi>, probably more than any poem of its
          time, moves easily from one social class to another, mixing themes of social idealism with
          the realities of everyday life. We should note here that “bourgeois realism” forms part of
          the mixed character of the romance mode. Like <hi rend="italic">King Horn</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Havelok</hi> shares with other romances the mixture of weird, supernatural
          events (the birthmark/light-from-the-mouth scenes) and very realistic, and often
          lower-class, detail: for instance, the dozen types of fish that Grim catches, or the
          peasant games at Lincoln. Havelok makes himself even lower than bourgeois, and both
          Godrich and Goldeboru show their disdain for lowly status by their reactions to the prince
          whom they think to be a churl.<note target="#7" type="footnotelink">7</note> These
          attitudes are not shared by Havelok, however, whose rewards to the loyal and disadvantaged
          at the end of the poem suggest a movement toward social amelioration. Characters who might
          otherwise be overlooked — Bertram the cook, the daughters of Grim the fisherman — thus
          attain noble status by the intervention of a king who has shared their experience.<note
            target="#8" type="footnotelink">8</note> As David Staines so aptly puts it, “Havelok is
          the embodiment of the ideal king from the point of view of the lower classes.”<note
            target="#9" type="footnotelink">9</note> That this late thirteenth-century romance is
          socially ameliorative is crucial to its tone and uncommon fusion of class values.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="4"><hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> as History and Myth</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="5"><hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> seemed as up-to-date and relevant
          as history to its early readers. Like many other medieval romances, it was even confused
          with history: one fourteenth-century Anglo-French chronicler, Peter de Langtoft,
          identifies Havelok with a Danish king named Gunter who made war on Alfred the Great.<note
            target="#10" type="footnotelink">10</note> Another fourteenth-century chronicler, Robert
          Mannyng of Brunne, corroborates the account in English but stops short when it comes to
          the question of how Havelok won England for lack of written historical documentation: “Bot
          I haf grete ferly that I fynd no man that has writen in story how Havelok this lond wan.”
          Nonetheless, there appears what scholars surmise to be a late interpolation of Havelok’s
          story in Mannyng’s chronicle.<note target="#11" type="footnotelink">11</note> Mannyng
          himself points to other kinds of evidence which suggests the existence of a local legend —
          a stone in Lincoln castle which is said to be the very stone that Havelok threw farther
          than the other contestants, and a chapel in which Havelok and Goldeboru were married.<note
            target="#12" type="footnotelink">12</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="4">There is yet another rather amazing piece of historical evidence to
          consider: the official thirteenth-century seal of the town of Grimsby, founded, the poem
          says, by Grim (lines 744–47). As if establishing its own claim to Havelok’s fame, the seal
          of Grimsby depicts its founder along with the hero and his betrothed, Goldeboru (see p. 72
          above). Grim’s figure, wielding the accoutrements of battle — shield and sword — looms
          large at the seal’s center, while Havelok is depicted in smaller proportions to the left,
          carrying a battle ax in one hand and a ring in the other; Goldeboru, also a smaller figure
          than the gigantic Grim, appears to the right, holding a scepter with one hand while her
          other is extended toward Havelok’s ring. Royal diadems hover over the heads of both
          Havelok and Goldeboru, while a providential hand at the top of the outer circle gestures
          toward the figures in the center. The seal’s inscription, which forms a circular frame for
          the three central figures, indicates the official status of the incorporation of Grimsby —
            <hi rend="italic">Sigillum Comunitatis Grimebye</hi>; all three figures are identified
          by name. That the seal stands as an emblem of corporate identity is clear. What is less
          clear is what the seal represents as historical evidence for the existence of Havelok.
          Perhaps what it ultimately suggests is the less-than-precise boundaries between history
          and myth.</p>
        <p style="body" n="5">If the question of defining boundaries between history and myth
          remains unanswered so too does the question of what a Danish prince is doing in a very
          English romance. Many scholars suggest that the Anglo-Norman <hi rend="italic">Lai
            d’Haveloc</hi> was probably composed in the Northeast Midlands (Lincolnshire/Humberside)
          where the Danes had once ruled and dominated linguistically. This would explain the
          persistence of a Danish legend if we assume a direct line of transmission between the
          Anglo-Norman poem and the English poem, an assumption that has met challenges in recent
          years. But even if <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> derives from a local oral tradition, as
          Nancy Mason Bradbury cogently argues, evidence still points to a locale that would have
          retained Scandinavian linguistic traditions and folkloric elements well into the late
          Middle Ages.<note target="#13" type="footnotelink">13</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="6">In fact, Piero Boitani calls <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> “a
          folk-tale thinly disguised as a romance.” Both W. R. J. Barron and Donald Sands describe
          the hero as a “male Cinderella.”<note target="#14" type="footnotelink">14</note> The
          themes of exile and return, taking revenge, and taking a bride recall similar folktale
          motifs. To probe a little deeper, a residue of mythology may lie behind certain other
          aspects of the poem, such as the identity of Grim. Edmund Reiss points out that the name
          Grímnir in the Old Norse sagas can mean “disguise,” and in several sagas Odin disguises
          himself as a servant or a ferryman. In one version of <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi>, Grim
          is a servant, and in another, a sailor. Digging even deeper, Reiss observes that “just as
          Odin the ferryman takes the dead heroes to Valhalla, so Grim takes Havelok to a new life.”
          Odin also keeps two ravens, Huginn and Muninn, who advise the god and bring news from
          around the world; in <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi>, one of Grim’s sons is named Hugh
            Raven.<note target="#15" type="footnotelink">15</note></p>
        <p style="heading" n="5">Dating and Provenance</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="6">The only complete manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi>
          appears in Bodleian MS Laud Misc. 108, dated c. 1300–25. The dialect of the poem seems to
          be Northeast Midlands, with both Northern and Southern forms.<note target="#16"
            type="footnotelink">16</note> As the introduction to <hi rend="italic">King </hi><hi
            rend="italic">Horn</hi> points out, both <hi rend="italic">Horn</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Havelok</hi> appear in this manuscript; both poems appear in the same
          hand. Also appearing are a variety of other writings (seventy all together, by Skeat’s
          count) including hagiography in a fifteenth-century hand, <hi rend="italic">The Vision of
            St. Paul</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">Disputatio inter corpus et </hi><hi rend="italic"
            >animam</hi>, and scientific information in a fifteenth-century hand. Rosamund Allen
          suggests that scribes who bound together the Laud MS may have included saints’ lives
          because the story of <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> itself is a kind of saint’s life, and
          Horn himself kills Saracen infidels and rebuilds churches; or else, “The empty folios of
          228v–237v were filled with saints’ legends and moral matter by a fifteenth century
          compiler who then bound related matter together.”<note target="#17" type="footnotelink"
            >17</note> As modern readers take the opportunity to read both poems in this volume,
          they may continue to observe and remark on parallels between the two poems that have often
          moved critics to consider them together.</p>

      </div>
      <div type="footnotes">

        <note type="footnote" n="1"><space rend="indent1"/>The earliest version is Geoffrei Gaimar’s
            <hi rend="italic">L’Estoire des Engleis</hi> written around 1140; the <hi rend="italic"
            >Lai </hi><hi rend="italic">d’Haveloc</hi>, written anonymously, follows shortly
          thereafter. See Alexander Bell, ed., <hi rend="italic">L’Estoire des Engleis by Geoffrei
            Gaimar</hi> (Oxford: Anglo-Norman Text Society, 1960); see also, Alexander Bell, ed.,
            <hi rend="italic">Le </hi><hi rend="italic">Lai D’Haveloc and Gaimar’s Haveloc
            Episode</hi> (Manchester: University of Manchester Press, 1925). Bell suggests that the
          writing of <hi rend="italic">Lai d’Haveloc</hi> may coincide with the incorporation of
          Grimsby in 1201.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="2"><space rend="indent1"/>See Donald G. Hoffman, “Malory’s
          Cinderella Knights and the Notion of Adventure,” <hi rend="italic">Philological
            Quarterly</hi> 67 (Spring 1988), 145–56. Havelok, as Malory’s Gareth, is trained first
          as a kitchen knave, a lowly position he transcends just as Cinderella does her domestic
          enslavement. Like many of Malory’s knights, Havelok has been recognized as a male
          Cinderella. See Russell A. Peck, <hi rend="italic">Cinderella Bibliography</hi>, <ref
            target="http://www.lib.rochester.edu/camelot/cinder/cinintro.htm" type="external"
            >http://www.lib.rochester.edu/camelot/cinder/cinintro.htm</ref>, under male
          Cinderellas.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="3"><space rend="indent1"/>Lee C. Ramsey, <hi rend="italic"
            >Chivalric Romances: Popular Literature in Medieval England</hi> (Bloomington: Indiana
          University Press, 1983), p. 36.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="4"><space rend="indent1"/>See Ernst Kantorowicz, <hi rend="italic"
            >The King’s Two Bodies: A Study in Mediaeval Political </hi><hi rend="italic"
            >Theology</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1957), for a discussion of the
          separation between the “office” of monarch and the monarch himself.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="5"><space rend="indent1"/>See J. Halverson in “<hi rend="italic"
            >Havelok the Dane</hi> and Society,” <hi rend="italic">Chaucer Review</hi> 6 (1971),
          142–51. John C. Hirsch argues against this view in “<hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> 2933: A
          Problem in Medieval Literary History,” <hi rend="italic">Neuphilologische
            Mitteilungen</hi> 78 (1977), 339–49.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="6"><space rend="indent1"/>Susan Crane, <hi rend="italic">Insular
            Romance: Politics, Faith, and Culture in Anglo-Norman and </hi><hi rend="italic">Middle
            English Literature</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1986), p. 47.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="7"><space rend="indent1"/>Robert Levine rejects the view that
          assumes differing literary tastes between the aristocracy and the bourgeoisie. See “Who
          Composed <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> for Whom?” <hi rend="italic">Yearbook of English
            Studies</hi> 22 (1992), 95–104. Levine also criticizes David Staines’ “attempt to
          harmonize the implied political agenda of the poem with its popular appeal” and notes that
          “the lower classes had more to lose at the hands of a tyrant than the barons did. . . .
          During the Middle Ages, the nobility and the lower classes certainly found themselves from
          time to time on the same side, sometimes in opposition to the king, sometimes in
          opposition to ecclesiastical authority, but which group was more strongly committed to its
          position seems a moot question” (p. 99).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="8"><space rend="indent1"/>It is important to point out that the
          marriages which occur at the end of the poem are a feature only of the English
          version.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="9"><space rend="indent1"/>David Staines, in “Havelok the Dane: A
          Thirteenth-Century Handbook for Princes,” <hi rend="italic">Speculum</hi> 51 (1976),
          602–23, especially p. 623, sees numerous parallels between Havelok and Edward I, as do
          Sheila Delany and Vahan Ishkanian. See “Theocratic and Contractual Kingship in <hi
            rend="italic">Havelok the Dane</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift </hi><hi
            rend="italic">für Anglistik und Amerikanistik</hi> 22 (1974), 290–302.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="10"><space rend="indent1"/>According to W. W. Skeat, ed., <hi
            rend="italic">The Lay of Havelok the Dane</hi>, second ed., revised by Kenneth Sisam
          (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1956), this appears in the Anglo-French Chronicle of Peter de
          Langtoft, “who died early in the reign of Edward II, and whose Chronicle closes with the
          death of Edward I. Here the only trace of the story is the mention of ‘Gountere le pere
          Havelok, de Danays Ray clamez’ — Gunter, father of Havelok, called king of the Danes. He
          identifies this Gunter with the Danish invader defeated by Alfred the Great, who in the A.
          S. Chronicle is called Godrum” (p. xliii).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="11"><space rend="indent1"/>See Idelle Sullens’ edition of <hi
            rend="italic">Robert Mannyng </hi><hi rend="italic">of Brunne: The Chronicle</hi>
          (Binghamton: Medieval &amp; Renaissance Texts and Studies, 1996), p. 499. This is known as
          the Lambeth interpolation.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="12"><space rend="indent1"/>Other evidence includes a reference to a
          boundary marker appropriately dubbed “Havelock’s Stone,” located near Grimsby. See W. W.
          Skeat, p. liii.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="13"><space rend="indent1"/>Nancy Mason Bradbury, “The Traditional
          Origins of <hi rend="italic">Havelok the Dane</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in
            Philology</hi> 90 (1993), pp. 117 ff. Indeed, the legend persisted in oral traditions
          into the seventeenth century, “when Gervase Holles recorded some variant versions of the
          tale from the townspeople of Grimsby” (p. 125).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="14"><space rend="indent1"/>Piero Boitani, <hi rend="italic">English
            Medieval Narrative in the 13th </hi><hi rend="italic">and 14th Centuries</hi>, trans.
          Joan Krakover Hall (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1982), p. 51. W. R. J. Barron
          says of the hero, “this male Cinderella accepts the ashes as his element” (p. 69). Donald
          Sands, in <hi rend="italic">Middle English Verse Romances</hi> (New York: Rinehart &amp;
          Winston, 1966) links the male Cinderella motif to the desires of the poem’s humble
          audience (p. 55). For a comprehensive discussion of male Cinderellas, see Eve Salisbury,
          “(Re)dressing Cinderella,” in <hi rend="italic">Retelling Tales</hi>, ed. Alan Lupack and
          Thomas G. Hahn (Rochester: D. S. Brewer, 1997), pp. 275–92.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="15"><space rend="indent1"/>Edmund Reiss, “<hi rend="italic">Havelok
            the Dane</hi> and Norse Mythology,” <hi rend="italic">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 27
          (1966), 115–24.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="16"><space rend="indent1"/>For further information on the dialect
          of <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> consult G. V. Smithers, ed., “Introduction” to <hi
            rend="italic">Havelok</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1987), pp. i–lxxxiii.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="17"><space rend="indent1"/>Rosamund Allen, <hi rend="italic">King
            Horn: An Edition Based on Cambridge </hi><hi rend="italic">University Library MS Gg.
            4.27</hi> (New York: Garland, 1984), p. 12.</note>


      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
