<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0"
  xml:id="Herzman-FourRomances-Export-03-Gen-Intro-tei">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>General Introduction</title>
        <author>Herzman, Ronald B.</author>
        <author>Drake, Graham</author>
        <author>Salisbury, Eve</author>
        <sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
        <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
        <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Amster, Mara I.</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Church, Jennifer</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Conrath, Ryan</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-09">Collected metadata</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-04">Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Encoded TEI</resp>
          <resp from="2025-08" to="2025-09">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-09">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-02" to="2025-09">Formatted for XML export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-09" to="2025-10">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Johnson-Olin, Martha M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName>
          <resp from="2023-12" to="2023-12">Collected metadata</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lupack, Alan</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>McShane, Kara L.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Roth, Aaron</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Saupe, Karen</persName>
          <resp>Collated and entered corrections</resp>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Encoded in TEI in 2025.</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
        </availability>
        <date/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Mara I. Amster</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Melissa Bernstein</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Jennifer Church</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rita Copeland</persName>
          <orgName>University of Minnesota</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Angela Gibson</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lisa J. Kiser</persName>
          <orgName>Ohio State University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Alan Lupack</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Russell A. Peck</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Ian Peddie</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Ann Robinson</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas H. Seiler</persName>
          <orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName>
          <orgName>University of Florida</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>John William Sutton</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Dana M. Symons</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName>
          <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <editor>Herzman, Ronald B.</editor>
            <editor>Drake, Graham</editor>
            <editor>Salisbury, Eve</editor>
            <title>Four Romances of England: King Horn, Havelok the Dane, Bevis of Hampton,
              Athelston</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
              <date>1999</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary
          texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered
          between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both
          affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the
          Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly
          interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and
          filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny
          from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to
          someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS
          publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and
          certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and
          apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other
          manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to
          ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original
          language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers
          expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s),
          textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and
          thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that
          set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor,
          congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current
          bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi
            rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
        <correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in
            order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and
            typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on
            Github:
            https://github.com/mets-editions/herzman-fourromances/blob/main/herzman-fourromances-export-corrections-log.xlsx</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>First edition published in 1999</change>
      <change>Encoded in HTML</change>
      <change>Entered editorial corrections in 2025</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <anchor xml:id="Herzman-FourRomances-Export-03-Gen-Intro"/>
      <div type="text">
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">The English word “romance” has accrued multiple meanings over the
          centuries: the joys of private love, heroic adventure on land and sea, the choice of the
          risky and exotic over the mundane. Romance is also a generic term that has been applied to
          such disparate works as ancient Hellenistic and Latin narratives, twentieth-century novels
          by authors such as Barbara Cartland, and even the mass-produced fantasies of Harlequin.
            <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi>, from which the word “romance” derives, is still the word
          used for “novel” in several modern European languages. The poems in this volume are also
          known as romances, a particular type of vernacular narrative which saw popularity in late
          medieval western Europe.</p>
        <p style="body" n="1">Of the four romances of England presented here, <hi rend="italic">King
            Horn</hi> (c. 1225) is probably the earliest (other than, arguably, Layamon’s <hi
            rend="italic">Brut</hi>, itself a translation of Wace’s twelfth-century Anglo-Norman
          poem on Arthurian themes).<note target="#1" type="footnotelink">1</note>
          <hi rend="italic">Havelok the Dane</hi> is dated at approximately 1290, with <hi
            rend="italic">Bevis of Hampton</hi> following shortly thereafter (about ten years before
          Dante began to write his <hi rend="italic">Divine Comedy</hi>). <hi rend="italic"
            >Athelston</hi>, the latest of the four, was probably composed between 1355 and 1399;
          thus it was completed shortly after Boccaccio’s <hi rend="italic">Decameron</hi> (1349–51)
          and around the time Chaucer was becoming the “father” of English poetry.</p>
        <p style="body" n="2">These were not the only English romances, of course. Romance was an
          extremely popular genre in medieval England; from the thirteenth through the fifteenth
          centuries dozens of English romances were produced, including, for example, <hi
            rend="italic">Guy of Warwick</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sir Perceval of Galles</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Sir</hi><hi rend="italic"> Isumbras</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Octavian</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Sir Eglamour of Artois</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sir Tryamour</hi>, and
            <hi rend="italic">Ywain</hi><hi rend="italic"> and Gawain</hi>; numerous retellings of
          Trojan and Theban history, the deeds of Alexander the Great and Richard the Lionhearted as
          well as the exploits of Charlemagne and his followers exist in Middle English versions;
          the legends of King Arthur and his knights, originally in Latin, French, and Welsh
          narratives, experienced a flowering in England in such classics as the <hi rend="italic"
            >Alliterative</hi><hi rend="italic"> Morte Arthure</hi> (c. 1350–1400) and <hi
            rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the Green</hi><hi rend="italic"> Knight</hi>. But the
          romances in this volume bring together some of the finest imaginative work in what became
          known as the Matter of England, the non-Arthurian romances dealing largely with English
          subjects and locales. They stand out as well by their reduced interest in the nuances of
          courtly behavior so characteristic of French romance, as they pay more attention to the
          socio-political issues contained within folktale motifs. Manuscript evidence suggests that
          romance reading in England was hardly confined to the nobility but became part of the
          increasingly prosperous and literate middle classes’ attempts to style themselves after
          the upper classes.<note target="#2" type="footnotelink">2</note></p>
        <p style="heading" n="1">Romance and the Epic</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="2">It was in the Middle Ages that the word “romanz” was first used
          to describe vernacular narratives as opposed to Latin poetry. But the meaning of the word
          narrowed to tales of knightly adventure and love together, linking the masculine,
          battlefield world of the <hi rend="italic">chanson de geste</hi> with the increasing
          upper-class interest in what we would now call “romantic love.” The idea of a personal
          love-interest between a man and woman, devoid of dynastic or financial concerns, had
          already taken root in the oral poetry of Provençal <hi rend="italic">trouvères</hi> and
          the court of Marie, Countess of Champagne, which produced courtly love debates and nuanced
          descriptions of love-relationships set down by her chaplain, Andreas, in his <hi
            rend="italic">De Amore</hi>. This combination of battlefield and boudoir, so to speak,
          is perhaps the chief way that romance diverges from epic. In the epic genre, an individual
          character of extraordinary strength demonstrates his martial skills and wisdom as he leads
          a nation or a group of comrades in great crisis — Odysseus in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Odyssey</hi>, Aeneas in the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>, Beowulf in his eponymous
          epic. While love interests are of some concern to the protagonist, they are incidental to
          larger dynastic and foundational concerns. For example, Odysseus’ return to Penelope is
          subordinated to his re-establishing the hereditary monarchy on Ithaca. Aeneas’ dalliance
          with Dido delays him from his ultimate goal: to win Italy for the Trojans and to found a
          line through marriage with King Latinus’ daughter, Lavinia. Indeed, Beowulf seems to have
          little intimacy beyond his band of warriors. Dynasty and glory are the point; love is
          not.</p>
        <p style="body" n="3">Romance itself can be distinguished in a number of other ways from
          epic. In the first place, it invests more heavily than epic in the personal story of the
          main character, in his response to challenges which test his strength, courage, and
          knightly courtesy. One can even argue that this happens in Arthurian legend, in which the
          dominance of the Round Table is eclipsed by the lonely quests for the Holy Grail or by the
          torn loyalties and madness of Lancelot or Tristan. At times, one may see, with Gabriel
          Josopovici, that fairy tale and romance “function in a timeless present in which the hero
          is the centre of the universe,” a paradigm in which the nation takes second place.<note
            target="#3" type="footnotelink">3</note> Another equally important component of the
          hero’s development is the challenge of love, making women major players in the action,
          whereas in epic women more usually lure the hero with dilatory lusts, commune weirdly with
          dead spirits, or stay at home and weave. And this greater centrality of women reminds us
          of the social and political functions of romance, which to many critics display a class
          consciousness and a certain anxiety over the instability of feudal relationships.</p>
        <p style="body" n="4">Romances, especially in England, nevertheless combine social realism
          with superhuman or supernatural events. This lends a “mixed” quality to romance, the
          combination of the real and the ideal. As W. R. J. Barron argues, romance is less a genre
          than a mode of writing:</p>
        <quote>The expressive conventions of the literary form reflect in their antithetical nature
          — adventure and instruction, fantasy and idealism, symbolism and realism — the mixed
          nature of the romantic mode, poised between the mythic and the mimetic. The tension
          between the various expressive means reflects the paradox within the mixed mode, which in
          turn reflects the dual nature of man as sensualist and idealist, escapist and moralist. .
          . . Throughout the Middle Ages [this mode] was all-pervasive, showing itself not only in
          almost every literary genre, including the professedly mimetic categories of chronicle,
          history, and biography, but in the other arts and even the forms and ceremonies of courtly
            life.<note target="#4" type="footnotelink">4</note></quote>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="3">The protean nature of romance, poised as it is between binary
          oppositions, or existing within a “mixed mode,” as Barron describes, renders a
          potentiality for expression and possibility for transformation that few other “modes of
          writing” can claim.<note target="#5" type="footnotelink">5</note> Thus what appears in the
          beginning to offer dim prospects for the future for a disenfranchised hero may be
          transformed into success by the end. Perhaps this marks yet another distinction between
          epic and romance. While epics often conclude in tragedy — the deaths of Hector, Beowulf,
          and Arthur in the <hi rend="italic">Alliterative Morte Arthure</hi>, even the “unfinished”
          twelfth book of the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi> which describes the death of Turnus but
          no actual wedding between Aeneas and Lavinia — romances are basically comic in structure.
          Life may be hard for Horn, Bevis, Havelok, or Athelston in the beginning, but by the end
          they receive rewards for their perseverance and valor: honor and glory for themselves,
          wedded bliss, and a restored kingdom to rule.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="2">The Character of the Romance Hero</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="4">While romances have a similar paradigm of exile and return, the
          development of the hero’s virtue through danger and hardship, there is no such singular
          scheme of romance composition. Sometimes, as in <hi rend="italic">King Horn</hi> or <hi
            rend="italic">Athelston</hi>, the structure is carefully symmetrical, while at other
          times it is more asymmetrical and episodic. The plot of <hi rend="italic">Bevis</hi>, for
          instance, is far more complicated, switching from one location to another or adding new
          adventures that do not seem to build on earlier adventures as keenly as in these shorter,
          relatively simpler romances. Often, the plot of a romance moves from a position of high
          privilege to a loss of that privilege followed by subsequent recovery. Horn, for instance,
          becomes a child exile, serves two different foreign kings to prove himself, and eventually
          wins back his rightful kingdom from Saracen invaders. Bevis’ mother sells him off to
          Armenian merchants; he later returns to oppose his stepfather and reclaim his
          patrimony.</p>
        <p style="body" n="5">This U-shaped motif (called the “monomyth” by such modern
          mythographers as Joseph Campbell)<note target="#6" type="footnotelink">6</note> is common
          to most epic and romance, and especially in romance it helps focus attention on the
          development of the central hero. Romance follows a pattern of separation and reunion or,
          as Northrop Frye views it, a journey of descent followed by ascent and a corresponding
          resolution of the hero’s purpose and place in the world.<note target="#7"
            type="footnotelink">7</note> Because the very structure of such romances is the
          development of the hero towards maturity, achievement, and resumption of his rightful
          title, they often focus on questions of identity — as initial concealment followed by
          gradual revelation. Havelok conceals his identity as a fisherman; Bevis becomes, at
          various points in the narrative, a shepherd, messenger, and pilgrim; Athelston begins as a
          lowly messenger but gradually grows into his identity as king.</p>
        <p style="body" n="6">Inevitably, the hero will have to prove himself through his valor by
          some test, usually in warfare. Romance tends to zero in on individual combat more than the
          expansive and highly exaggerated battle scenes of epic. The chivalric code, not always
          explicitly spelled out in romance, is nevertheless implied in the bravery, justice, and
          glory of knightly combat — as, for instance, in the single combat between Yvor and Bevis
          on an island, and the bravery and triumph that the hero asserts throughout his life.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="3">The Politics of Love and Class</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="5">A significant love-relationship, usually ending in marriage, is
          not only integral to romance as a genre but also to the hero’s development. Typically, the
          hero will fall in love with a high-born woman, whom he marries only after significant
          obstacles impeding their union have been overcome. Both Horn and Bevis nearly lose their
          loved ones in marriage to an evil or unwanted man; a neat variation on the idea occurs in
            <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi>, as Goldeboru is forced to marry against her will a man
          she thinks is a vulgar peasant, only to discover by a sign from heaven that the peasant is
          Havelok, of royal lineage equal to her own. In <hi rend="italic">Bevis</hi> Josian endures
          two forced marriages to unsavory men until she is finally wedded to her beloved. For Dame
          Edyff and Athelston’s queen it is not marital union that is impeded, but reunion and
          reconciliation of family members brought about through their personal sufferings.</p>
        <p style="body" n="7">The reason these women figure so prominently, in fact, has mostly to
          do with heterosexual love and courtship. Yet the hero is not always the active pursuer and
          agent, nor is his female counterpart always the hapless damsel in distress. As if
          demonstrating the inherent power of transformation, gender roles can surprisingly reverse
          themselves in romance. Goldeboru, for example, often acts as an equal partner and
          companion to Havelok. Rymenhild — dismissed by some readers as a cardboard character known
          mostly for her overwhelming passions — takes the lead in wooing the gallant young Horn.
          Dame Edyff and Athelston’s queen demonstrate an integrity and fortitude that set an
          example for the men around them, while Josian, one of the most active and well-developed
          of all medieval heroines, shows remarkable strength through a series of amazingly adverse
          situations. Medieval romance heroines, just as women in the real medieval world, are
          prohibited from participating in military combat, but they take an active role in personal
          relationships in these narratives. This may be in part because the relatively new concept
          of romantic love in companionate marriage was making its way into popular culture.
          Marriage was slowly moving away from being mostly an exchange of property (the woman and
          her dowry being the items of exchange) and towards a loving if not always socially equal
            partnership.<note target="#8" type="footnotelink">8</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="8">The importance of women to romance reminds us that issues of gender in
          these tales are intertwined with matters of class and the vicissitudes of political power
          in medieval England. Some political issues had already become ancient history: the attacks
          by the Saracens in <hi rend="italic">Horn</hi> are probably memories of the Viking
          invasions that had plagued England in the ninth to eleventh centuries. A world that joined
          a son of Southampton with the daughter of the King of Armenia in <hi rend="italic">Bevis
            of Hampton</hi> may have had its historical roots in England’s active role in the
          Crusades of the eleventh and twelfth centuries. In <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>, trial
          by ordeal recalls an already discarded practice. Yet the power struggle between the king
          and clergy in this romance was a continual reality in England. From the Crusades to the
          Barons’ Revolts and the civil uprisings of 1381 to armed conflict with France in the
          Hundred Years’ War, the unglamorous realities of war were well known to the English.</p>
        <p style="body" n="9">Besides conflict between royalty and clergy, English romance reveals
          the changing status of the nobility. Throughout the later Middle Ages, the nobility faced
          innovative legal arrangements and centralized royal power on the one hand and the growing
          power of the mercantile classes on the other. The increasing practice of primogeniture
          created an uneasy position for the younger sons of noble families with no inheritance and
          little else to do except take holy orders or fight. Stephen Knight argues that the figure
          of the solitary knight, who must prove himself in arms by winning back his patrimony,
          reflects this uneasy position in contemporary English life.<note target="#9"
            type="footnotelink">9</note> In such “family romances” as <hi rend="italic">Amis</hi><hi
            rend="italic"> and Amiloun</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Avowing of Arthur</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">King Horn</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>, Knight sees that
          “competitive assertiveness is the inner strain upon the fraternal bond [between
            knights].”<note target="#10" type="footnotelink">10</note> But even in the imaginative
          world of romance, the solitary chivalric hero is sometimes overpowered by a dialectic of
          multiple interests — as Knight observes, <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> “shows
          ‘lower-class’ features in its village games and physical work, royal myth in its hero and
          his revelation, urban connections in its links to an origin legend for Grimsby. This text
          is much broader than the specifically knightly and feudal world, being both older than and
          marginal to the main romance pattern.”<note target="#11" type="footnotelink">11</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="10">A threat from below was imposing even more reality on English romance
          in the changing value of peasant labor in the fourteenth century and in an independent
          merchant class that would eventually replace feudal society with a dependence on money,
          capital, deeded property, and litigation. Indeed, congruent with a genre aware of the
          vicissitudes of contemporary daily life, there is an engaging realism in these romances.
            <hi rend="italic">Havelok</hi> features lists of particular fish on sale in Lincoln, and
          the hero engages in peasant wrestling contests. Horn is a convincing sooty beggar when he
          decides to approach Rymenhild in disguise. <hi rend="italic">Athelston</hi>’s four main
          characters are initially messengers before they acquire higher social status. Bevis plays
          various roles from the lower classes before regaining his patrimony. Furthermore, local
          colors in the form of place names and graphic descriptions of a variety of battles and
          methods of execution point to the realities of social and political discontent emanating
          from the lower classes. Even so, Barron’s reading of the Matter of England romances
          suggests a caveat against universalizing class analysis. In comparison to the models of
          French Romance, “The struggles in which [English romance heroes] are caught up spring not
          from the internal contradictions of courtly codes but the oppressive forces of a wicked
            world.”<note target="#12" type="footnotelink">12</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="11">Everyday life in this wicked world nonetheless comes with eerie
          surprises. In the simple home of the fisherman Grim, Havelok is identified as a special
          figure by a mysterious light and a cross-shaped birthmark. Much of the plot of <hi
            rend="italic">Athelston</hi> hangs on a miraculous outcome of a trial by ordeal; Bevis
          is often saved <hi rend="italic">deus-ex-machina</hi> style from certain death. Such
          intrusions of the supernatural mark the romance hero’s life as rather extraordinary. The
          very real and immediate body of the hero becomes the slate upon which the truth of God’s
          will is indelibly and infallibly written. It is this combination of supernaturalism and a
          kind of homey realism that gives the Middle English romances in this volume the
          distinctive “mixed” quality so often seen as definitive of the notion of romance.</p>

      </div>
      <div type="footnotes">

        <note type="footnote" n="1"><space rend="indent1"/>See Introduction to <hi rend="italic"
            >King Horn</hi> in this volume for an alternative dating of <hi rend="italic">King
            Horn</hi> in the middle of the thirteenth century.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="2"><space rend="indent1"/>W. R. J. Barron, <hi rend="italic"
            >English Medieval Romance</hi> (London: Longman, 1987), p. 54. See also Derek Pearsall,
          “The Development of Middle English Romance,” <hi rend="italic">Mediaeval Studies</hi> 27
          (1965), 91–116; Susan Crane, <hi rend="italic">Insular</hi><hi rend="italic"> Romance:
            Politics, Faith, and Culture in Anglo-Norman and Middle</hi><hi rend="italic"> English
            Literature</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1986); Harriet Hudson,
          “Middle English Popular Romances: The Manuscript Evidence,” <hi rend="italic"
            >Manuscripta</hi> 28 (1984), 67–78.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="3"><space rend="indent1"/>Gabriel Josopovici, <hi rend="italic">The
            Book of God: A </hi><hi rend="italic">Response to the Bible</hi> (New Haven: Yale
          University Press, 1988), p. 199.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="4"><space rend="indent1"/>Barron, pp. 5–6.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="5"><space rend="indent1"/>For a comprehensive discussion of the
          hybrid nature and transformative potential of romance see Kevin and Marina Scordilis
          Brownlee, <hi rend="italic">Romance: Generic Transformation from</hi><hi rend="italic">
            Chrétien de Troyes to Cervantes</hi> (Hanover: University Press of New England,
          1985).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="6"><space rend="indent1"/>See Joseph Campbell, <hi rend="italic"
            >The Hero with a</hi><hi rend="italic"> Thousand Faces</hi> (New York: Pantheon,
          1949).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="7"><space rend="indent1"/>Northrop Frye, <hi rend="italic"
            >The</hi><hi rend="italic"> Secular Scripture: A Study of the Structure of Romance</hi>
          (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1976).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="8"><space rend="indent1"/>For general discussions of medieval
          marriage, see Georges Duby, <hi rend="italic">Medieval Marriage: Two Models from
            Twelfth</hi><hi rend="italic">-Century France</hi>, trans. Elborg Forster (Baltimore:
          The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1978), and Frances and Joseph Gies, <hi rend="italic"
            >Marriage and the</hi><hi rend="italic"> Family in the Middle Ages</hi> (New York:
          Harper and Row, 1987), especially pp. 141 ff. See also Christopher Brooke, <hi
            rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> Medieval Idea of Marriage</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
          University Press, 1989).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="9"><space rend="indent1"/>Stephen Knight, “The Social Function of
          the Middle English Romance.” In <hi rend="italic">Medieval Literature: Criticism,
            Ideology, &amp; History</hi>, ed. David Aers (New York: St. Martin’s Press, Inc., 1986),
          p. 107.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="10"><space rend="indent1"/>Knight, p. 113.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="11"><space rend="indent1"/>Knight, pp. 109–10.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="12"><space rend="indent1"/>Barron, p. 85.</note>


      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
